Guide to the Jean Starr Untermeyer Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jean Starr Untermeyer papers
1924-1970
YCAL MSS 52
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.39
(3 boxes)
The Jean Starr Untermeyer Papers contain correspondence, photographs, book reviews, obituaries, poems, offprints, newspaper clippings, and miscellaneous papers.
Untermeyer, Jean Starr, 1886-1970
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift and bequest of Jean Starr Untermeyer. See Description of the Papers for more information.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
JEAN STARR UNTERMEYER, 1886-1970
Jean Starr Untermeyer, poet and former wife of the poet Louis Untermeyer, was born in 1886 in Zanesville, Ohio, to Abram E. and Johanna S. Starr. She attended Columbia University but broke off her studies there in 1907 to marry Louis Untermeyer. Later she envisioned a career as a singer of lieder, debuting in Vienna in 1924, but eventually discontinued that pursuit.
Upon discovering that she had been writing poems secretly for years, her husband encouraged her and submitted her works to magazines. Growing Pains, her first volume of poetry, was published by B. W. Huebsch in 1918. In 1925, the Untermeyers were divorced. They later remarried but were again divorced in 1951. Their only son Richard died while a sophomore at Yale University in 1927.
The following year Untermeyer began work as a translator. Her major effort in this genre was Hermann Broch's The Death of Virgil (1945). She and Broch met at Yaddo in 1939 and remained intimate friends until Broch's death in 1951.
Untermeyer wrote a number of book reviews for The Saturday Review, The New York Times, and other publications. She taught at writers's conferences at Olivet College in Michigan in the 1930s and lectured at The New School for Social Research from 1948 to 1951. Her major poetry collections include Dreams Out of Darkness (1921), Steep Ascent (1927), The Winged Child (1936), and Love and Need (1940). Private Collections, her autobiography, was published in 1965.
Jean Starr Untermeyer died in New York City in July 1970.
Scope and Contents
The Jean Starr Untermeyer Papers contain correspondence, photographs, book reviews, obituaries, poems, offprints, newspaper clippings, and miscellaneous papers. The materials span the years 1924 to 1970, with the bulk falling between 1940 and 1965. The collection consists of papers inserted in the books of Jean Starr Untermeyer's personal library. She gave and bequeathed her library to the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library in 1969 and 1971, respectively, in honor of her son who died at Yale University in 1927. She donated her personal papers to the library of the State University of New York at Buffalo.
The first section of the papers contains correspondence from others to Jean Starr Untermeyer. Much of this consists of letters and cards from aspiring poets, accompanying the gift of a recently published volume of poetry, such as those from Gladys Greene and Polly Hanson. There is also correspondence from publishers who have sent complimentary copies of books or express thanks for permission to reprint material, such as New Orlando Publications and Crown Publishers. Some letters seek advice, while others show appreciation for praise and encouragement, such as those from Max and Fanny Berman, Sue Abbott Boyd, and Hazel Hutchinson. A few simply contain greetings and news from friends, such as Alys Bentley, Bryher, Connie Carrier, Michel Farano, Nandor Fodor, Djane Hearst, Eric Mendelsohn, and Edith Sitwell. Folder 25 contains letters from the poet and critic Joel Keith. Letters from The Saturday Review and Simon and Schuster concern business matters.
The second section, Photographs, includes pictures of Hermann Broch, Michel Farano, Allen Tate, and Jean Starr Untermeyer, along with photographs of her childhood home in Zanesville, Ohio.
The third section, Miscellaneous Papers, includes book reviews of Bryher's The Player's Boy and Edith Sitwell's autobiography Taken Care Of, obituaries of Nandor Fodor, a controversial psychoanalyst, and Erich Kahler, cultural historian and close friend of Hermann Broch, along with offprints of articles by Lancelot Law Whyte, and poems translated by Untermeyer. Folder 48 contains an epistolary biography of Carl Heinrich Hertz, a German officer in World War I, who was killed in 1918.
Poets, American; Women poets -- United States; Diaries; Photographs; Broch, Annemarie Meier-Graefe; Broch, Hermann, 1886-1951; Bryher, 1894-1983; Farano, Michel Batta; Fodor, Nandor, 1895-1964; Hertz, Carl Heinrich, 1893-1918; Hutchinson, Hazel Collister; Keith, Joel; Mendelsohn, Eric; Sitwell, Edith, 1887-1964; Untermeyer, Jean Starr, 1886-1970
- Correspondence, 1940-59
  - Ackland, Valentine, 1940-59 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Allen & Co. (J. A. Allen & Co.), 1952 Jul 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Atkins, Russell, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bentley, Alys, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Berman, Max and Fanny, 1939-50 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Boyd, Sue Abbott, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Broch, Annemarie Meier-Graefe ("Buch"), 1951 Jul 26 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bryher, 1945-51 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Carrier, Constance ("Connie"), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cook, William, 1957 Apr 26 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Crown Publishers, Inc., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Farano, Michel Batta, 1943-59, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Fodor, Nandor, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Folsom, Franklin, 1938 Apr 15 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Garrigue, Jean, 1961 Jun 28 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Glass, Ada M., 1965 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Greene, Gladys, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hanson, Pauline ("Polly"), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Hearst, Djane, 1947-50 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Herring, Robert, 1935 Aug 13 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Hurd, Pearl S., 1967 Feb 5 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Hutchinson, Hazel Collister, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Jiménez, Juan Ramón, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Kahler, Antoinette, 1945 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Keith, Joel, 1950-53, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Loveman, Amy
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: The Saturday Review, Box 1, folder 33
  - Marx, Anne, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Mendelsohn, Eric, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Murray, Pauli, 1962 Oct 13 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - New Orlando Publications, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Rosenfeld, Paul L., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Roth, Julie, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Sachs, Charlotte, 1948 Apr 11 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - The Saturday Review, 1951 Nov 29 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Simon and Schuster, Inc. (concerning Hermann Borchardt), 1943 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Sitwell, Edith, 1950-51 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Tas, Helen Teschner, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Vrbovska, Anca
    See: New Orlando Publications, Box 1, folder 29
  - Warner, Sylvia Townsend (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Unidentified, 1927-65, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence removed from Untermeyer's books., 1923-1969, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 61-63)
    Scope and Contents
    Correspondents include Ann Adams, Hermann Broch, Toni Cassirer, and Antoinette Kahler.
- Photographs
  - PEOPLE
    - Broch, Hermann, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - [Farano ?], Michel, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Tate, Allen, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Untermeyer, Jean Starr, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - BUILDINGS
    - Untermeyer, Jean Starr: childhood home, Zanesville, Ohio, 1965 Jun (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Unidentified church, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Unidentified house, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - OBJECTS
    - Cameo ring, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Miscellaneous Papers, 1924-1970
  - Diary, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Aus den Briefen von Carl Heinrich Hertz, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Bryher, The Player's Boy: book review by Marianne Moore, 1953 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Fodor, Nandor
    - "Analytical Disc Jockey," The New Yorker (article about Fodor), 1949 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Obituary, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Hunter College, Associate Alumnae of: Annual Breakfast, program [JSU spoke on "A Parable of Poetry"], 1941 Feb 15 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Kahler, Erich: obituary, 1970 Jun 30 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Poems translated by JSU, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Sitwell, Edith, Taken Care Of: book review by Alan Pryce-Jones, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Urzidil, Johannes: printed poem ("Jahrestag"), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Whyte, Lancelot Law
    - "The Growth of Ideas": offprint, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - "Time and the Mind-Body Problem": offprint, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Newspaper article on lecture, "The Development in Man," The Prattler, 1966 Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Other papers, 1953, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Inscriptions removed from Untermeyer's books, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Printed material (Box 3, Folder 66-93)
    • Advertisement of Jean Starr Untermeyer's translation of Hermann Broch's The Death of Virgil. • Advertisement for MacDowell Colony. • Advertisement forRubaiyat of Omar Khayyam with an introduction by Louis Untermeyer. • Akeley, T. Barton. TS. • Demcourier. Autumn 1939. Issue dedicated to Louis Untermeyer. • Farano, Michel. Intaglios. • House of Books catalogue. • A List of the First 774 Books Published for American Armed Forces Overseas. • Menashe, Samuel. There is No Jerusalem But This. Inscribed to Jean Starr Untermeyer. • NY Herald Tribune. TS. • Miscellaneous advertisements (3 folders). • Miscellaneous articles inscribed to Jean Starr Untermeyer. • Miscellaneous newspaper clippings (8 folders). • Miscellaneous postcards. • O'Gorman, Ned. Dust jacket for The Buzzard and the Peacock. • Pearson, Lester B. "Freedom, Security and Brotherhood" • Program for an exhibition of paintings by Pamela Bianco. • Program. Philharmonic Society of New York, 1921-1922. • Program. Prayer of Youth. Inscribed to Jean Starr Untermeyer. • Speyer, Leonora. House of Calvin inscribed to Jean Starr Untermeyer. • Urzidil, Johannes. Uber Das Handwerk. Inscribed to Jean Starr Untermeyer. Laid in: a poem translated by Jean Starr Untermeyer. • Walt Whitman. Pamphlet poetry series.